Changes in your diet not
only affect you physically,
physiologically inside,
but also mentally,
how well you think,
psychologically,
how well you feel.
But you’ll never know just
how good you can feel
until you put it to the test
and try eating healthy.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we look at the not so
sweet side of sweeteners
and we start with
one called erythritol.
It’s funny, when you search
for information
about the low-calorie
sweetener erythritol
in the scientific literature,
you stumble across papers like this,
describing a use for erythritol
that I had not imagined.
But you think that’s explosive?
What about headlines like these?
Erythritol associated with increased
body fat in young adults,
metabolic dysfunction,
coronary heart disease,
heart failure, pre-diabetes,
full-blown diabetes,
and diabetic complications
like kidney damage and blindness.
But wait,
I thought erythritol
has been reported
to be a totally safe
and even have
anti-oxidant properties.
Let’s take a closer look
at these studies.
Upon entering college,
many young adults
experience weight gain—
the dreaded “freshman 15”—
which can start them off
on the wrong course in life
in terms of developing
chronic illness.
But not all freshmen do;
so, researchers wanted to try
to tease out why some
gained weight
and others didn’t.
So, on one of their
first days at school
a bunch of students
got their blood drawn,
and then nine months later
were reweighed
and got more blood taken.
About a quarter of the students
maintained a stable weight,
but the other three quarters gained
an average of about nine pounds.
Then, they did something
interesting.
They pooled the blood of all
those who remained stable
and compared that
to the collection
of blood from all
the gainers
to see if they could
pick out any differences.
And the ones who gained weight
had significantly higher levels
of erythritol in their blood,
and not just by a little—
15 times higher levels.
Those found to have poor
blood sugar control
had 21 times higher
blood erythritol levels.
And the same thing
with heart disease.
What did people
who developed heart disease
have more in their blood
than those that didn’t?
Erythritol!
The same thing with diabetes
and diabetes complications.
Okay, so what’s going on?
Is erythritol contributing to obesity,
and heart disease, and diabetes,
or is it just
an innocent bystander?
Maybe it’s reverse causation,
meaning instead of erythritol
leading to more weight gain,
maybe weight gain
led to more erythritol.
After all, who tends to go
for the low-calorie sweeteners?
But wait a second.
In this study, for example,
they took blood before
and after a period of over 20 years.
Was erythritol
even around back then?
The first blood draws
were in the 80s,
and erythritol wasn’t
approved until 2001.
Same thing with
the heart disease study.
The blood samples
were taken in the late 80s;
so, the presence of erythritol
in their blood cannot be explained
by consumption of erythritol
as a sugar replacement.
So, wait.
How did they end up
with so much erythritol
in their system?
Their own body made it.
We know that your body
can take excess blood sugar
and convert it into erythritol.
If you give people
radioactively labeled sugar,
within two hours
radioactively labeled erythritol
shows up in your blood.
It turns out erythritol
is a pentose-phosphate
pathway metabolite,
meaning that’s the pathway
by which blood sugar
is converted into erythritol.
And the pentose-phosphate pathway
is a protective pathway.
It's a way your body disposes
of excess blood sugar
by trying to convert
the sugar to other things
to bring down blood sugar levels.
So, having erythritol
in your system
seems to be a consequence
of too high sugars, not the cause.
So, no wonder erythritol
is associated with diabetes.
That may be just like saying
high blood sugar levels
are associated with
high blood sugar levels.
And high blood sugars
are also associated
with obesity and heart disease.
In fact, erythritol synthesis
could be an adaptive mechanism
to counter the oxidative stress
induced by obesity
and high blood glucose.
In other words, not just
a way to reduce blood sugar,
but since erythritol
can act as an antioxidant,
maybe your body
is making it
specifically to help
sop up the mess.
The bottom line is that
there are no studies
linking the consumption
of erythritol
to any disease outcomes.
But the flip side
of that is yeah,
the studies that have been
done on erythritol do show
it to be relatively innocuous
and possibly beneficial,
but the effects of chronic
erythritol consumption
have not been evaluated
either way.
That’s where the science was,
until 2023, when a prestigious lab
out of Cleveland Clinic
found increased clotting
susceptibility in human blood
in a test tube and mouse
blood in a mouse artery.
That was at blood concentrations
like 45 micromoles, or even 290.
But have people chug two
tablespoons of the stuff
and erythritol blood levels
jump up into the thousands
within a matter of minutes.
And so, until we have clinical
studies exonerating the stuff,
I would recommend people to
stay away from erythritol.
Next up, we look at the conflicting
data on the intake of aspartame,
sold as Nutrasweet,
with respect to non-
Hodgkin’s lymphoma,
multiple myeloma,
leukemia,
and pancreatic cancer.
The approval of aspartame
has a controversial history.
The FDA Commissioner concluded that
there was reasonable certainty
that human exposure to aspartame
would not pose a risk
of brain damage
resulting in mental retardation,
hormonal dysfunction, or both;
and will not cause
brain tumors,
however, the FDA’s own
Public Board of Inquiry
withdrew their approval
over cancer concerns.
Furthermore, several
FDA scientists advised
against the approval,
citing the Aspartame company’s
own brain tumor tests.
The Commissioner approved
aspartame anyway,
before he left the FDA and enjoyed
a thousand dollar a day
consultancy position with the
aspartame company’s PR firm.
Then the FDA actually prevented the
National Toxicology Program (NTP)
from doing further
cancer testing,
so we were left with people battling
over different rodent studies,
some of which showed
increased cancer risk
and some
that didn’t.
Reminds me of the whole
saccharin story,
where it caused bladder
cancer in rats, but not in mice,
leaving us with
unanswerable questions like,
"So, are we more
like a rat or a mouse?"
We obviously had to put the aspartame
question to the test in people,
but the longest human safety
study lasted only 18 weeks.
We needed better
human data.
Since the largest rat study
highlighted lymphomas and leukemias,
the NIH-AARP study tracked
blood cancer diagnoses…
and higher levels
of aspartame intake
were not associated
with the risk of cancer.
It’s a massive study,
but was criticized
for only evaluating relatively
short-term exposure—
people were only
studied for 5 years.
Hey—better than 18 weeks.
But how about 18 years?
All eyes then
turned to Harvard,
which started following
the health and diets
of medical professionals since before
aspartame even came on the market.
In the most comprehensive
long-term population study
to evaluate the
association
between aspartame intake
and cancer risk in humans,
they did find an association
between both diet soda
and total aspartame intake and the
risks of non-Hodgkin’s lymphoma
and multiple myeloma in men
and leukemia in
both men and women.
OK, but why more cancer
in men than women?
A similar result was found for
pancreatic cancer and diet soda.
Not soda in general,
in fact the only sugar tied
to pancreatic cancer risk
was the milk
sugar, lactose.
It was the diet soda.
So the male/female
discrepancy
could have just been
a statistical fluke,
but they decided to
dig a little deeper.
Aspartame is broken
down into methanol,
and the methanol is
turned into formaldehyde,
a documented human carcinogen.
The same enzyme that
detoxifies regular alcohol
is the same enzyme that
converts methanol to formaldehyde.
Is it possible men
just have higher levels
of this enzyme
than women?
Yes. That’s why women get
higher blood alcohol levels
drinking the same
amount of alcohol.
If you look at liver samples
from men and women,
there’s significantly greater
enzyme activity in the men.
So maybe that explains the
increased cancer risk in men—
the higher conversion rates
from aspartame to formaldehyde.
But how do we
test it though?
Ethanol—regular alcohol—
competes with methanol for
this same enzyme’s attention.
In fact regular alcohol is
actually used as an antidote
for methanol poisoning.
So men who
don’t drink
may have higher formaldehyde
conversion rates from aspartame
if this whole formaldehyde
theory is correct.
And indeed, consistent
with this line of reasoning,
it was the men that
drank the least alcohol
that appeared to have the
greatest cancer risk from aspartame.
A third cohort study
has since been published
and found no increased
lymphoma risk
associated with
diet soda
during a ten year
follow-up period.
So no risk detected
in the 18 week study,
the 5 year study or
the 10 year study,
only in the
18 year study.
What should we
make of all this?
Some have called for a re-evaluation
of the safety of aspartame.
The horse is kind of
"out of the barn" at this point
with 34 million pounds of
the stuff produced annually,
but that doesn’t mean
we have to eat it,
especially, perhaps, pregnant
women and children.
Finally today, the natural plant-based
sweeteners stevia and monk fruit
are pitted head-to-head against
aspartame and Splenda.
A number of artificial sweeteners have
been FDA-approved in North America,
including aspartame and sucralose
(sold as Splenda).
But, there are also
natural high-intensity sweeteners
found in plants.
The global market for non-nutritive
sweeteners in general, these non-caloric
sweeteners, is in the billions,
including all the artificial ones—
and two natural ones
extracted from plants:
stevia and monk fruit.
I’ve done a video about stevia;
what about monk fruit?
The fruits of Luo Han
Guo—monk fruit in Chinese—
have evidently been used for hundreds
of years as a natural
sweetener and folk medicine.
The non-caloric sweet taste
comes from mogrosides,
a group of cucurbitane-type
triterpene glycosides that
make up about 1% of the fruit,
and are like hundreds of times
sweeter than sugar.
The mixed mogrosides
have been estimated
to be about 300 times as sweet
as table sugar, such that an 80% extract
was nearly 250 times sweeter than sugar.
If you read reviews in
Chinese natural medicine journals,
you’ll see pronouncements like this:
monk fruit has been shown to have
anti-coughing effects, anti-asthma,
anti-oxidation, liver-protection,
blood sugar-lowering, immuno-regulation,
and anti-cancer.
But, what they don’t tell you up front
is that they’re talking about reducing
ammonia-induced mouse coughs.
A natural food sweetener with
anti-pancreatic cancer properties?
Monk fruit “may be used for daily
consumption as an additive in foods
and drinks to prevent or
treat pancreatic cancer.”
Yeah, maybe in your pet mouse.
And, the anti-proliferative activity
of monk fruit in colorectal cancer
and throat cancer was on colorectal
and throat cancer cells in a petri dish.
Now, they did show mogrosides killing
off colorectal cancer cells
and throat cancer cells,
and our digestive tract could be
directly exposed to these compounds
if we ate them, but what’s missing?
Right, they didn’t test it
against normal cells.
You could pee in a petri dish
and kill off cancer cells.
The whole point is to find something
that kills off cancer but
leaves normal cells alone,
something that they weren’t
able to show here.
Are there any human
studies on monk fruit?
No, …
until now.
Owing to the rapidly growing popularity
of natural plant-based sweeteners,
they thought it would be of interest
to determine whether natural sweeteners
would be a healthier alternative
to sugar or artificial sweeteners.
So, they randomized people to drink
an aspartame sweetened beverage
versus monk fruit sweetened,
versus stevia
versus table sugar.
And then they measured blood sugars
over 24 hours, and there was
no significant difference found
between any of them.
But, wait a second.
The sugar group was given
16 spoonfuls of sugar,
the amount of added sugar in a
20-ounce bottle of Coke.
So, the other three groups consumed
16 less spoonfuls of sugar
and still had the same
average blood sugars?
But, table sugar causes a big
blood sugar spike.
Here it is; I’ll show you.
Drink that bottle of sugar water
with its 20 sugar cubes worth of sugar,
and your blood sugars jump 40 points
over the next hour.
Whereas, you give them an aspartame
sweetened beverage, or monk fruit,
or stevia, and nothing happens,
which is what you’d expect, right?
These are non-caloric sweeteners,
no calories.
It’s just like you’re drinking water,
right?
So, how could your daily blood sugar
values average out the same?
The only way that could happen is if
the non-calorie sweeteners maybe made
your blood sugar spikes worse
somehow later in the day?
Look what happens when you give people
Splenda mixed with sugar water.
You get a greater blood sugar spike,
a greater insulin spike chugging the
sugar with sucralose than without,
even though Splenda alone causes
no spike of its own.
So, does aspartame do the same thing?
At the one-hour mark,
they fed people a regular lunch.
And, so, the blood sugars went back up
and down as they normally
would after a meal.
Not spiking as high as
drinking straight sugar water,
just a gentle up and down.
OK, but that was in the group that
drank the sugar an hour before.
In the group that drank the aspartame,
even though their blood sugars didn’t rise
at the time, an hour later at lunch,
they shot up higher, as if the person
had just drank a bottle of soda.
OK, but what about the natural sweeteners,
stevia and monk fruit?
Same thing.
Same exaggerated blood sugar spike
to a regular meal taken an hour later.
So, you can see how it all equals out
in terms of average blood sugars
even though in these three
non-caloric sweetener groups,
they took in 16 spoonfuls less sugar,
at least in part because they ate more.
After drinking a Diet Coke,
you’re more likely
to eat more at your next meal than
drinking a regular Coke.
In fact, so much more
that the energy 'saved'
from replacing sugar with non-caloric
sweeteners was fully compensated for
at a subsequent meal;
hence, no difference in total daily
calorie intake was found.
The sugar-sweetened beverage led to
large spikes in both blood
sugar and insulin,
whereas these responses were higher
for the three other beverages
following the lunch later.
So, when it came to calorie intake,
or blood sugars, or insulin spikes,
they were all just as bad.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the NutritionFacts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and the “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.